Chapter 34. The cabin table.
It is noon and Doughboy the steward thrusting his pale loaf of bread face
from the cabin scuttle announces dinner to his lord and master who sitting in
the Lee quarterboat has just been taking an observation of the sun and is now
mutely reckoning the latitude on the smooth medallion-shaped tablet reserved
for that daily purpose on the upper part of his ivory leg from his complete
inattention to the tidings you would think that moody Ahab had not heard is
menial, but presently catching hold of the mizen shrouds, he swings himself to
the deck, and in an even unexilated voice, saying, "Dinner, Mr. Starbucks,"
disappears into the cabin.
When the last echo of his sultan's step has died away, and Starbucks, the first
Emir, has every reason to suppose that he is seated, then Starbucks rouses from
his quietude, takes a few turns along the planks, and after a grave peep into
the binnacle, says with some touch of pleasantness, "Dinner, Mr. Stub!" and
descends the scuttle. The second Emir lounges about the rigging a while, and
then, slightly shaking the main brace to see whether it will be all right with
that important rope, he likewise takes up the old burden, and with a rapid
dinner, Mr. Flask, follows after his predecessors.
But the third Amir, now seeing himself all alone on the quarter deck, seems to
feel relieved from some curious restraint, for tipping all sorts of
knowing winks in all sorts of directions, and kicking off his shoes,
he strikes into a sharp but noless squall of a hornpipe right over the
Grand Turk's head, and then by a dextrous slight, pitching his cap up
into the misen top for a shelf, he goes down rollicking, so far at least as he
remains visible from the deck, reversing ing all other processions by bringing up
the rear with music. But air stepping into the cabin doorway below, he pauses,
ships a new face altogether, and then, independent, hilarious little flask,
enters King Ahab's presence, in the character of Abjectis, or the slave.
It is not the least among these strange things bred by the intense
artificialness of sea usages that while in the open air of the deck some
officers will upon provocation bear themselves boldly and defyingly enough
towards their commander yet 10 to one let those very officers the next moment
go down to their customary dinner in that same commander's cabin and
straightway they're inoffensive not to say deprecatory and humble heir towards
him as he sits at the head of the table.
This is marvelous, sometimes most comical. Wherefore this difference, a
problem? Perhaps not. To have been Belchazar, king of Babylon, and to have
been Belshazar not haughtily but courteously, therein certainly must have
been some touch of mundane grandeur. But he who in the rightly regal and
intelligent spirit presides over his own private dinner table of invited guests,
that man's unchallenged power and dominion of individual influence for a
time. That man's royalty of state transcends Belshazar's, for Belshazar
was not the greatest. He who has but once dined his friends has tasted what
it is to be Caesar. It is a witchery of social zarship which there is no
withstanding. Now if to this consideration you super add the official
supremacy of a shipmaster, then by inference you will derive the cause of
that peculiarity of sea life just mentioned.
Over his ivory inlaid table, Ahab presided like a mute maimed sea lion on
the white coral beach, surrounded by his warlike but still differential cubs. In
his own proper turn, each officer waited to be served. They were as little
children before Ahab, and yet in Ahab there seemed not to lurk the smallest
social arrogance. with one mind their intent eyes all fastened upon the old
man's knife as he carved the chief dish before him. I do not suppose that for
the world they would have profained that moment with the slightest observation,
even upon so neutral a topic as the weather. No. And when reaching out his
knife and fork between which the slice of beef was locked, Ahab thereby
motioned Starbucks plate towards him, the mate received his meat as though
receiving alms, and cut it tenderly, and a little started, if per chance the
knife grazed against the plate, and chewed it nolessly, and swallowed it,
not without circumspection.
For like the coronation banquet at Frankfurt, where the German emperor
profoundly ds with the seven imperial electors, so these cabin meals were
somehow solemn meals eaten in awful silence. And yet at table old Ahab
forbad not conversation, only he himself was dumb. What a relief it was to
choking stub when a rat made a sudden racket in the hold below. And poor
little flask, he was the youngest son and little boy of this weary family
party. His were the shin bones of the saline beef. His would have been the
drumsticks. For Flask to have presumed to help himself, this must have seemed
to him tanamount to larseny in the first degree. Had he helped himself at that
table, doubtless never more would he have been able to hold his head up in
this honest world. Nevertheless, strange to say, Ahab never forbad him, and had
Flask helped himself, the chances were Ahab had never so much as noticed it.
Least of all did Flask presume to help himself to butter, whether he thought
the owners of the ship denied it to him, on account of its clotting his clear,
sunny complexion, or whether he deemed that on so long a voyage in such
marketless waters, butter was at a premium, and therefore was not for him a
sub altern. However it was, Flask, alas, was a butterless man.
Another thing, Flask was the last person down at dinner, and Flask is the first
man up. Consider, for hereby Flask's dinner was badly jammed in point of
time. Starbucks and Stub both had the start of him, and yet they also have the
privilege of lounging in the rear. If Stub even, who is but a peg higher than
Flask, happens to have but a small appetite, and soon shows symptoms of
concluding his repass, then Flask must be stir himself. He will not get more
than three mouthfuls that day, for it is against holy usage for Stub to proceed
Flask to the deck. Therefore, it was that Flask once admitted in private that
ever since he had arisen to the dignity of an officer, from that moment he had
never known what it was to be otherwise than hungry, more or less, for what he
ate did not so much relieve his hunger as keep it immortal in him. Peace and
satisfaction, thought flask, have forever departed from my stomach. I am
an officer, but how I wish I could fish a bit of old-fashioned beef in the
folks, as I used to when I was before the mast. There's the fruits of
promotion now. There's the vanity of glory. There's the insanity of life.
Besides, if it were so that any mere sailor of the Peekquad had a grudge
against Flask in Flask's official capacity, all that sailor had to do in
order to obtain ample vengeance was to go a at dinnertime and get a peep at
Flask through the cabin skylight, sitting silly and dumbfounded before awful Ahab.
Now Ahab and his three mates formed what may be called the first table in the
Peekquad's cabin. After their departure, taking place in inverted order to their
arrival, the canvas cloth was cleared, or rather was restored to some hurried
order by the palid steward, and then the three harpooners were bidden to the
feast, they being its residuary leges.
They made a sort of temporary servants hall of the high and mighty cabin.
In strange contrast to the hardly tolerable constraint and nameless
invisible doineerings of the captain's table was the entire carefree license
and ease, the almost frantic democracy of those inferior fellows, the
harpooners. While their masters, the mates, seemed afraid of the sound of the
hinges of their own jaws. The harpooners chewed their food with such a relish
that there was a report to it. They dined like lords. They filled their
bellies like Indian ships all day loading with spices. Such portentious
appetites had quag and tachego that to fill out the vacancies made by the
previous repast often the pale doughboy was fained to bring on a great baron of
salt junk seemingly quarried out of the solid ox. And if he were not lively
about it, if he did not go with a nimble hop, skipping a jump, then Tashego had
an ungentlemanly way of accelerating him by darting a fork at his back harpoon-wise,
and once Dagu, seized with a sudden humor, assisted Doughboy's memory by
snatching him up bodily, and thrusting his head into a great empty wooden
trencher, while Tashego, knife in hand, began laying out the circle preliminary
to scalping him. He was naturally a very nervous, shuddering sort of little
fellow, this bread-faced steward, the progeny of a bankrupt baker and a
hospital nurse. And what with the standing spectacle of the black terrific
Ahab, and the periodical, tumultuous visitations of these three savages,
Doughboy's whole life was one continual lip quiver. Commonly, after seeing the
harpooners furnished with all things they demanded, he would escape from
their clutches into his little pantry.
adjoining and fearfully peep out at them through the blinds of its door till all was over.
It was a sight to see Quiquated over against Tashego, opposing his filed
teeth to the Indians, crosswise to them, Dagu seated on the floor, for a bench
would have brought his hearse plumemed head to the low car lines at every
motion of his colossal limbs making the low cabin framework to shake as when an
African elephant goes passenger in a ship. But for all this, the great Negro
was wonderfully abstious, not to say dainty. It seemed hardly possible that
by such comparatively small mouthfuls he could keep up the vitality diffused
through so broad, baronial, and superb a person. But doubtless this noble savage
fed strong and drank deep of the abounding element of air, and through
his dilated nostril snuffed in the sublime life of the worlds, not by beef
or by bread or giants made or nourished.
But Quiquake, he had a mortal, barbaric smack of the lip in eating, an ugly
sound enough, so much so that the trembling doughboy almost looked to see
whether any marks of teeth lurked in his own lean arms. And when he would hear
Tashego singing out for him to produce himself, that his bones might be picked,
the simple, witted steward all but shattered the crockery hanging round him
in the pantry by his sudden fits of the palsy. Nor did the wet stone which the
harpooners carried in their pockets for their lances and other weapons, and with
which wet stones at dinner they would ostentatiously sharpen their knives.
That grading sound did not at all tend to tranquilize poor Doughboy. How could
he forget that in his island days Quequake, for one, must certainly have
been guilty of some murderous convivial indiscretions. Alas, Doughboy, hard
fairest the white waiter who waits upon cannibals. Not a napkin should he carry
on his arm, but a buckler. In good time, though, to his great delight, the three
salt sea warriors would rise and depart, to his credulous, fablemongering ears,
all their marshall bones jingling in them at every step like Moorish scimitars in scabbards.
But though these barbarians dined in the cabin and nominally lived there, still
being anything but sedentary in their habits, they were scarcely ever in it
except at meal times, and just before sleeping time when they passed through
it to their own peculiar quarters. In this one matter, Ahab seemed no
exception to most American whale captains, who as a set rather inclined
to the opinion that by rights the ship's cabin belongs to them, and that it is by
courtesy alone that anybody else is at any time permitted there, so that in
real truth the mates and harpooners of the Peekquad might more properly be said
to have lived out of the cabin than in it. For when they did enter it, it was
something as a street door enters a house, turning inwards for a moment,
only to be turned out the next, and as a permanent thing residing in the open
air. Nor did they lose much hereby. In the cabin was no companionship.
Socially, Ahab was inaccessible, though nominally included in the census of
Christendom, he was still alien to it.
He lived in the world as the last of the grizzly bears lived in settled Missouri.
And as when spring and summer had departed that wild Logan of the woods,
burying himself in the hollow of a tree, lived out the winter there, sucking his
own paws, so in his inclement, howling old age, Ahab's soul, shut up in the
caved trunk of his body, there fed upon the sullen paws of its gloom.